Mss.Rec.1 Mss.Rec.1
American Philosophical Society
Ottawa material
1947-1948
Mss.Rec.1
American Philosophical Society
14.0 Reel(s)
This collection consists of Ottawa songs, interviews, word lists, legends, Nanabojo stories, autobiographical stories, and information on Ottawa history. Some of the material is given in both Ottawa and English, some in Ottawa only. Recorded by Jane Ettawageshik in Michigan from 1947 to 1948.
21 sound tape reels (8 hr., 28 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, full track, mono; 5 in. and 7 in.
Chingwa, Joe
Cooper, Victoria
Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969
Ettawageshik, Jane Willets, 1915-1996
Related Archival Materials
Related manuscript material, including texts written in Ottawa by Chief Ettawageshik, interlinear translations, and word lists are available in the Franz Boas Collection of Materials for American Linguistics (Mss.497.3 B63c.)
Transcription, parallel, and interlineal translation of 14 Ottawa stories (on original wire spools 1-5), made by Howard Webkamigad in 2001, is also available. As of January 2011, this material is uncatalogued and held in manuscripts processing.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Jane Ettawageshik in 1950. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Scope and Contents note
This collection has two series. Series 1 consists of original tapes 1a, 2b, 3b, and 4a. The contents of these tapes were originally recorded onto discs in 1947 and were transferred to sound tape reels in 1949. Series 2 consists of original tapes 1b, 2a, 3a, 4b, and 5 through 16. The contents of these tapes were originally recorded on 13 wire spools in 1947 and were transferred to sound tape reels in 1949.
Nanabush (Legendary character); Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa Indians--Music; Ottawa Indians--Social life and customs; Ottawa language; Sound recordings
- Series 1, Mss.Rec.1.1
  - How the Bear Lost his Tail, 1947-08; 01A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:40; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Scope and Contents note
    Recorded by Jane Willets from Chief Fred Ettawageshik on Presto Recorder discs in 1947, then transferred to open tape reels in 1949. Mss. of material recorded written in Ottawa by Chief Ettawageshik with inter-linear translations. Chief Ettawageshik is from Harbor Springs, Michigan.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Bears; Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - The Legend of Manitou Islands and Sleeping Bear Point, 1947-08; 01A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:59; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    North Manitou Island (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Philadelphia (Pa.); Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); South Manitou Island (Mich.)
  - The Story of the Choke Cherries, 1947-08; 01A-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - The Story of Nanabojo and the Leeks, 1947-08; 01A-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - Wooden Whistles, 1947-08; 01A-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:22; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Story of the origin of a belief that blowing whistles will call up snakes in the springtime. Recorded by Jane Willets from Chief Fred Ettawageshik on Presto Recorder discs in 1947, then transferred to open tape reels in 1949. Mss. of material recorded written in Ottawa by Chief Ettawageshik with inter-linear translations. Chief Ettawageshik is from Harbor Springs, Michigan.
    Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.); Snakes; Whistles
  - Why Some Trees have Knobs on Them and the Birches Grow in Clumps, 1947-08; 01A-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Birch; Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.); Trees--Folklore
  - The Legend of the Serpent, 1947-08; 01A-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:04; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A legend told to Chief Ettawageshik by Chief Joe Chingwa of Petoskey, Mich. Recorded by Jane Willets from Chief Fred Ettawageshik on Presto Recorder discs in 1947, then transferred to open tape reels in 1949. Mss. of material recorded written in Ottawa by Chief Ettawageshik with inter-linear translations. Chief Ettawageshik is from Harbor Springs, Michigan.
    Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.); Snakes
  - The Legend of the Corn, 1947-08; 02B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:46; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Corn; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Why the Birchbark has Streaks, 1947-08; 02B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:07; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Birch; Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - The Story of Bagog, the Skeleton, 1947-08; 02B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:49; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A story describing puberty fasting. Recorded by Jane Willets from Chief Fred Ettawageshik on Presto Recorder discs in 1947, then transferred to open tape reels in 1949. Mss. of material recorded written in Ottawa by Chief Ettawageshik with inter-linear translations. Chief Ettawageshik is from Harbor Springs, Michigan.
    Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.); Puberty rites; Skeleton--Folklore
  - Underground People, 1947-08; 02B-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:26; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996; Ettawageshik, Joe
    "The Origin of the Pipigwe or 'Little Hawk' lineage to which Chief Ettawageshik belongs through his father. As written by Joe Ettawageshik, Fred's father, and edited by Fred." Recorded by Jane Willets from Chief Fred Ettawageshik on Presto Recorder discs in 1947, then transferred to open tape reels in 1949. Mss. of material recorded written in Ottawa by Chief Ettawageshik with inter-linear translations. Chief Ettawageshik is from Harbor Springs, Michigan.
    Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Word list from "Why Some Trees have Knobs on Them", 1947-08; 02B-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:45; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.); Trees--Folklore
  - Word List from "Wooden Whistles", 1947-08; 02B-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:36; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - Word list from "The Story of Bagog, the Skeleton", 1947-08; 03B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:29; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - Creation of Mackinac Island by Nanabojo, 1947-08; 03B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Mackinac Island (Mich.: Island); Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - The Legend of Harbor Point, 1947-08; 03B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:33; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - The Story of the Robin, 1947-08; 03B-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:55; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.); Puberty rites; Robins--Folklore
  - Word list from "Underground People", 1947-08; 03B-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:54; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - Nanabojo Creates the Indian, 1947-08; 03B-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:18; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - Nanabojo Creates the Indian [second telling by Fred Ettawageshik], 1947-08; 04A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:49; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - Why the Great Lakes are Receding, 1947-08; 04A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:14; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Great Lakes (North America); Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Interview between Jane Willets and Chief Ettawageshik, 1947-08; 04A-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:11; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Hunting; Interviews; Native American histories; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Philadelphia (Pa.)
- Series 2, Mss.Rec.1.2
  - Ottawa story, 1948-05; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:57; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Contents not clearly identifiable from collection's documentation. Most likely a folkloric story. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Wire recording) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Ottawa story, 1948-05; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:14; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Contents not identifiable from collection's documentation. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
  - Ottawa song, 1948-05; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:18; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Contents not clearly identifiable from collection's table of contents. May be "Puberty Fast Song," described as "Joe Chingwa's own composition... supposed to be sung by a boy undergoing the puberty fast in his little lodge." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa Indians--Music; Puberty rites
  - Ottawa story, 1948-05; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:39; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - The Rabbit and the Lynx, 1948-05-01; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:49; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949. Original wire recording for this program was transferred to two different tapes in two sections due to apparent wire malfunction on first transfer. The two transfers have been spliced together with no loss of original content. Splice occurs at 03:57.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Lynx--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Rabbits--Folklore
  - The Man Carried off by an Eagle (Thunder), 1948-05-02; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:29; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A myth describing the origin of naming ceremonies. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Ottawa language
  - Nanaboju Cycle, 1948-05-02; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:02; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A cycle of stories about Nanaboju including his early life. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Kidnappers from Saginaw, 1948-05-02; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:24; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A semi-historical legend about a child snatched from the Harbor band by hostile Indians from Saginaw. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Kidnapping; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa Indians--Social life and customs; Ottawa language
  - Legend describing Sorcery ("Bear Walking"), 1948-05-04; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:41; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "Narrator introduces her story with the words, 'Minawa dibadjmowin', 'Another legend' because she had previously told another legend about sorcery which was recorded on this same spool. The wire in this section of spool became so tangled, however that we were unable to save it. Victoria Cooper re-told this first story later on [APSdigrec_0584]" Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Brothers--Folklore; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Witchcraft--Folklore
  - The Chief with Seven Sons, 1948-05-05; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:03; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Legend of an Ottawa woman kidnapped by the Sioux and the death of the Sioux chief's seven sons, each of whom tried successively to marry her. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Forced marriage; Kidnapping; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa language; Petoskey (Mich.)
  - Family of Bears, 1948-05-06; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:27; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A legend of two children who were kidnapped by bears. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Bears--Folklore; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Kidnapping; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Kidnapping, 1948-05-06; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:04; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A semi-historical legend of a kidnapping from the Burt Lake band. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Kidnapping; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Legend of the Green Corn, 1948-05-05; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:51; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "The story describes the origin of corn. The Ottawa version includes a prophecy by the beautiful woman who gave the Indians the corn plant that the land on which the hunter (to whom she appeared) is standing will some day be lost to the Indian. This is not in the English translation." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Corn--Folklore; Hunters--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Petoskey (Mich.); Visions
  - Legend of the Green Corn, 1948-05-05; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:25; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
  - The Fleet-footed Woman, 1948-05-05; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:38:53; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A legend about the adventures of a man and a sorceress. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Petoskey (Mich.); Witchcraft--Folklore; Witches--Folklore
  - Nanaboju and the Bears [1 of 2], 1948-05-20; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:41; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "A long myth describing the killing of Nanaboju's younger brother, Jibiabos, by bears in retaliation against Nanaboju for killing the bears' grandfather and devouring the meat. In this mythological time there was really no such thing as death, so that Nanaboju sees his brother again after the bears have killed him. Then follows a conversation between the two brothers in which it is decided that it is better for people and animals to die when they are killed and for their souls to follow the spirit path to the west because otherwise all nature would have to stay in mourning. Nanaboju commands his brother to blaze the the spirit path and to rule over the land of the dead in the west. Jibiabos leaves singing the mournful death chant." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Bears--Folklore; Future life; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Mkkwániwi at Burt Lake, 1948-05-20; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:25; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "Description of a frightening experience of Joe Chingwa's and Fred Ettawageshik's grandfather while hunting at Burt Lake." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Burt Lake (Mich.); Harbor Springs (Mich.); Hunting; Ottawa Indians--Biography; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa language
  - Ottawa Hymns at Tabandong Feast, 1948-05-01; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:25; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996; Sagataw, Hattie
    "The singing of the old Roman Catholic hymns based on French airs, in the Ottawa language, is not customary now at the Tabandong feast. They are usually sung only at wakes these days. On this occasion the hymns were sung by the host and hostess and the guests so that I could record them.... Old hymnals compiled by missionaries in Ottawa-Ojibwa dialect were used." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Catholic Church--Hymns; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Music; Ottawa Indians--Religion; Ottawa Indians--Social life and customs; Ottawa language
  - Origin of Red Osier, 1948-04-30; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:32; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Ducks--Folklore; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Nanabush (Legendary character)--Legends; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Legend of the Maškuo'tens, 1948-04-30; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:29; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Story of an Ottawa battle with the Indians who formerly lived in the same region of Michigan. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa language
  - Nanaboju and the Bear's Skull, 1948-04-30; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:22; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "Further adventures of Nanaboju, the Ottawa culture hero." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
  - Christening Ceremony, 1948-05-01; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:39; Ettawageshik, Fred, 1896-1969; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "A speech and chant with horn rattle accompaniment of the kind used at a naming ceremony following an Ottawa feast. The speech is what Fred Ettawageshik remembered saying when he performed the ceremony at my adoption at the King's Supper, Jan. 6 1947." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949. Naming ceremony speech only transferred to reel-to-reel.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Ottawa language
  - Ottawa-English Conversation at Tabandong Feast, 1948-05-01; 07-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:24; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996; Kishigo, Joe
    Conversation; Fasts and feasts; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Social life and customs; Ottawa language
  - Legend describing sorcery ("Bear walking"), 1948-05-20; 07-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:28; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A story describing sorcery practiced by one brother against another. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
  - Description of life at Seven Mile Point, etc., 1948-05-20; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:08; Cooper, Victoria; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Autobiographical material from 80-year-old Victoria Cooper's girlhood at Seven Mile Point and first years at Harbor Springs. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Social life and customs; Ottawa language
  - Nanaboju and the Bears [2 of 2], 1948; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "An incident to added to the end of the first (1) story [APSdigrec_0038]" Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Audiocassette) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
  - The Magic Arrow, 1948-06; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:55; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A legend about a poor boy who married the chief's daughter because of his possession of a magic arrow. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Marriage--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - The Fastest Flying Bird, 1948-06; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:10; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A story of a race held by birds in which the crane was the winner. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Birds--Folklore; Cranes (Birds)--Folklore; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Racing--Folklore
  - The Cricket and the Ant, 1948-06; 10-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:49; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Ants--Folklore; Crickets--Folklore; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Insects--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - The Snow Ball, 1948-06; 10-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:25; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A story about the battle of winter and spring. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Seasons--Folklore; Spring--Folklore; Winter--Folklore
  - A Girl Married to a Dog, 1948-06; 10-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:41; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A story describing the marriage of a girl and a dog and the tragedy that resulted in the Ottawa prohibition against the marriage of a human to an animal. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Dogs--Folklore; Harbor Springs (Mich.); Human-animal relationships; Marriage--Folklore; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - The Two Sisters, 1948; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:56; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    A semi-historical legend about two sisters of the Harbor band. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Michigan; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language; Sisters
  - Mkkwániwi at Sleeping Bear Point, 1948; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:26; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    "Another incident from the eventful life of Joe's grandfather told by Joe." Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Michigan; Ottawa Indians--Biography; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa language
  - Mkkwániwi and the Trial at St. Joseph, 1948; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:02; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996
    Description of a murder trial in which Mkkwániwi was one of the judging chiefs. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Michigan; Ottawa Indians--Biography; Ottawa Indians--History; Ottawa Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.; Ottawa language; Trials (Murder)
  - Conversation among 8 Ottawa at Cross Village, 1948; 13-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:33; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996; Norton, Bill, Mrs.
    Informal group conversation in English with some Ottawa words. A short story about an Ottawa chief named Sagima is told in English by Mrs. Bill Norton, starting at 01:34. Originally recorded on wire recorder in 1948 and transferred to reel-to-reel tape in 1949.
    Conversation; Cross Village (Mich.); Fish; Ottawa Indians--Folklore; Ottawa language
  - Death Song, 1948; 17-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:46; Chingwa, Joe; Ettawageshik, Jane, 1915-1996